RG 170:001, Mansfield Training School
Connecticut State Library
Mansfield Training School records
1863-1992
Connecticut State Library
Mansfield Training School (Mansfield Depot, Conn.)
122 cubic feet
The Mansfield Training School opened on July 1, 1917 as a home for persons with mental retardation. It closed in 1993.
RG170_001
1991-072; Series 6 also includes 1992-055
Historical Note
The Mansfield Training School was established in 1917 with the merging of two institutions, the Connecticut Colony for Epileptics and the Connecticut Training School for the Feeble Minded (previously known as the School for Imbeciles) "to provide for the care, custody, education and employment of mental defective (feeble minded) and epileptic persons."1 On its opening on July 1, 1917 there were 402 students in residence.
The population and campus steadily expanded for the next fifteen years. By 1932, there were 1,070 residents, 559 males, 511 females.2 However, the next decade was a trying time as the depression and World War II affected Mansfield Training School. Even as the institution reached and maintained its projected maximum population, the waiting list for entry increased to over a thousand prospective people, prompting the state to open Southbury Training School in the 1940s. Cuts in the operating budget, no construction on urgently needed buildings, the lack of adequate maintenance on contemporary equipment and buildings and insufficient staff strained the quality of the services.
The next few decades following the war were marked by changes at the school. The 1950s saw an increase in construction, which included the Longley School and four new dormitories with 152 beds each. However, chronic overcrowding continued to be a problem. The number of residents and the types of education and training increased. Residents worked in the print, wood working, weaving, and industrial shops.3 As the number of people who worked outside of the school increased they were also provided with more realistic job training.4
A change in the attitude towards the mentally challenged became increasingly evident in the 1960s. There was an increase of the ratio of the number of staff to residents. In 1969 there were 1,609 residents and 875 full time staff.5 The size of the campus reached 1,000 acres and had 85 buildings. The administration sought to lessen the institutional aspects of life at the school and increase activity in things like the Special Olympics.6 The objective of the school also reflected this change, "1. to rehabilitate as many retarded persons as possible so that they can return to the community as self-supporting citizens and 2. to assist other retarded persons …who do not have the capacity to return to the community, to become as happy and self sufficient as possible."7 However, the staff was always challenged to provide quality care for such a large number of residents.
The next two decades continued the trend towards a less institutionalized attitude concerning the care and services for the mentally challenged. Cottages were created on campus and more people moved into group homes located in communities around the state. In 1976 the number of residents had dropped to 1,106.8 The facilities were old and the quality of care was questioned by family members of residents in a 1978 lawsuit, CARC v. Thorne that would eventually result in the closing of the school in 1993. However, the number of residents had been dropping steadily for years. Since 1984, an average of 80 men and women left the school each year. By 1991 there were 141 residents remaining.9 In 1993 the last buildings were closed as the last residents left for other accommodations. Some buildings were so dilapidated by this time that they were knocked down, other buildings were transferred to the use of other institutions such as the University of Connecticut and still others were abandoned.
Endnotes
1Annual Report, 1948-1949, 2.
2Governor's Digest, 1932, 5.
3Annual Report, 1951-1952, 7.
4Annual Report, 1953-1954, 5.
5Annual report, 1968-1969, 2.
6Ibid, 13.
7Ibid, 1968-1969, 2.
8Annual Report 1976, 5.
9Kathleen Megan, "Mansfield: End of an Institution Memories of Mansfield, Closing After 76 Years", Hartford Courant, January 31, 1993, A1.
See also the.
Scope and Content
Series 1. Predecessor Institutions, 1863-1919, includes the records of two institutions that merged to form the Mansfield Training School: the Connecticut School for Imbeciles, located in Lakeville, Connecticut, and the Connecticut Colony for Epileptics, located on the grounds of what became the Mansfield Training School. The Connecticut School for Imbeciles records, 1863-1917, include resident commitments, admission and attendance, personnel and financial information. The Connecticut Colony for Epileptics records, 1911-1919, 1931, consist of research notes, resident commitments, admission and attendance, personnel, financial and facility and land information.
Series 2. Board of Trustees, 1917-1974, includes minutes, superintendent's reports, and Parole Board minutes that reflect the changing attitudes towards the mentally challenged during the beginning decades of the twentieth century through the first few years of the 1970s.
Series 3. Administration, circa 1891-1987, Superintendents' Files, 1919-1971; Joint Committee of Training Schools minutes, 1947-1951, 1968-1969; appointment books, 1956-1957, 1962-1963, 1981; donation records, 1963-1965; and various publications.
Series 4. Mansfield Training School Foundation, 1972-1991, includes the Board of Directors minutes and correspondence. The Foundation was a non-profit organization, comprised mostly of family and friends of residents at the school, to raise money for equipment and programs for the school.
Series 5, Civil Defense, 1943-1955, contains the functional and organizational plan, and forms and informational brochures for the Civil Defense Organization that was based at the Mansfield Training School in case of a threat against the United States, particularly a nuclear attack.
Series 6.Residents, 1884-1986, which comprises the bulk of the collection, includes birth certificates, death certificate receipts, commitment orders, admission and discharge/transfer information, roll call books, register cards, medical records at department levels and for individual residents, charts and files related to residential life, recreational, social and religious activities. The separate accession of 1992 -055 consists of 24 boxes of the case records of discharged residents compiled by the Social Service Department of the Mansfield Training School covering the time period 1920-1959. In addition the series contains outpatient files, circa 1929-1959.
Series 7. Personnel, 1912-1989, complements the resident records. They provide not only information on the administrative side of the operations but also the care and training of residents and the size and variety of staff needed to support the residents and to carry out the mandate of the institution. Records include employment agreements, employee information and departure/transfer index cards and binders, time cards, dismissal and legal action, meeting notes, notices and procedures and newsletters.
Series 8. Finances, 1916-1981, contains various expense and payroll records.
Series 9. Reports, 1917-1990, shows the number and variety of reports required both internally and externally at the school and the importance of statistical data. Population/attendance reports in different formats and medical reports comprise a large segment of this series. Annual reports provide information about what the school accomplished over a given year, major events, admissions, needs, financial statements, statistics, and departmental reports. Reports done by outside agencies are also included, such as the Connecticut Study of Known Retarded Persons that documented all the residents' functional, self-care, social competence, behavior and physical status on a scale.
Series 10. Facilities, 1888-1992, includes real estate deeds and leases, land and building information, maps and blueprints, and proposed construction and land uses.
Series 11. Photographs and slides, circa 1927-1991, depicts the routines and daily life of residents and staff including the training residents received, work residents did on the farm and throughout the campus, and recreational, social and religious activities. Special events are also documented such as theatrical productions, holiday celebrations and excursions. In addition to the aforementioned, training demonstrations and presentations comprise a large segment of the slides. Facilities and educational and entertainment slides represent a much small proportion of the slides.
Series 12. Scrapbooks, 1946-1956, includes one scrapbooks that contains newspaper clippings related to issues and events of the mentally challenged in general and in Connecticut, particularly Southbury and Mansfield Training Schools and another about events and people associated with Mansfield Training School.
Series 13. Artifacts, circa 1949-1975, includes items related to residents and staff.
Series 14. Training, circa 1968-1984, includes audio tapes, video cassettes, films, LPs, and manuals produced both internally and by outside parties.
Arrangement
Arranged into fourteen series as follows:
Series 1. Predecessor Institutions, 1863-1919; Series 2. Board of Trustees, 1917-1974; Series 3. Administration, circa 1891-1987; Series 4. Mansfield Training School Foundation, 1972-1991; Series 5, Civil Defense, 1943-1955; Series 6.Residents, 1884-1986; Series 7. Personnel, 1912-1989; Series 8. Finances, 1916-1981; Series 9. Reports, 1917-1990; Series 10. Facilities, 1888-1992; Series 11. Photographs and slides, circa 1927-1991; Series 12. Scrapbooks, 1946-1956; Series 13. Artifacts, circa 1949-1975; and Series 14. Training, circa 1968-1984.
Related Material
RG 170, Dept. of Developmental Services, Series 2, Commissioner, Legal files, CARC v. Thorne
Index Terms
Organizations:
Mansfield Training School (Mansfield Depot, Conn.); Connecticut School for Imbeciles; Connecticut Colony for Epileptics
Places:
Mansfield Conn.); Salisbury (Conn.)
Subjects:
Mansfield Training School (Mansfield Depot, Conn.) -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut School for Imbeciles -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut Colony for Epileptics -- Records and correspondence; Children with mental disabilities -- Education -- Connecticut; Developmentally disabled children -- Education -- Connecticut; Children -- Institutional care -- Connecticut -- Mansfield; People with mental disabilities -- Institutional care -- Connecticut -- Mansfield; Mental retardation facilities -- Connecticut -- Mansfield; Developmentally disabled -- Institutional care -- Connecticut -- Mansfield
Document Types:
Audiocassettes; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Correspondence; Journals (accounts); Ledgers (account books); Lists (document genres); Manuals (instructional materials); Medical records; Minutes; Newsletters; Pamphlets; Personnel records; Photographs; Reports; Slides (photographs); Videocassettes
Restrictions on Access
New Exemption: Public Act 11-242, section 37 amends subsection (b) (10) of Conn. Gen. Stat. sec. 1-210 and adds to the exemptions of the Freedom of Information Act any records created as a result of a doctor-patient or a therapist-patient relationship. This closure applies to all records listed below as Restricted.
Residents: Files continue to be made available to residents themselves upon reliable proof of identification which may be a current copy of a Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or current credit card with the patient's name on it.
Families: Section 52-146c of the Connecticut General Statutes allows "next of kin" the right to view records of a deceased patient who was also a relative.
Relatives of deceased residents should e-mail or send a letter to Assistant State Archivist Allen Ramsey with the following information:
- Full name of the resident.
- Approximate years resident was at Mansfield Training School.
- Name, e-mail, and telephone of the requestor.
The State Archives will search for the folder and will report the results of the search to the requestor. If a file is found and the requestor wants to view or receive copies of the file, the following information must first be presented to the State Archivist:
- Proof of identity through a copy of a current Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or a copy of a current credit card with the requestor's name on it.
- Proof that the patient is deceased through a copy of a death certificate or obituary.
- Proof that the requestor is a "next of kin" to the deceased patient through a copy of a birth certificate, obituary with the name of the requestor mentioned as a survivor, or a signed and dated notarized statement of relationship to the resident.
Other Parties: According to the new exemption, medical records are closed to other parties.
Record Series Listed Below: Records listed below labeled as non-restricted or unrestricted are open to all researchers who have read the rules of use and signed the registration forms. Since these records are stored off site, they may not be available on the same day.
See the policy.
Provenance
Most of this material was acquired during the summer and fall of 1991. The Mansfield Training School staff transferred the remainder as the institution closed out the buildings during the winter and spring of 1992. The University of Connecticut transferred the outpatient files in the spring of 2010.
Container List
- Series 1. Predecessor Institutions, 1863-1919
  Boxes 1, 4-5, 7 and items 2-3, 6 are RESTRICTED.
  Boxes 1A and 8 are UNRESTRICTED.
  - Connecticut School for Imbeciles, 1863-1917
    - Death certificate stubs, 1909 August 4-1917 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      RESTRICTED
    - Commitment orders (Box 1)
      - B-C, 1897-1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - D-F, 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - G-H, 1887-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - J-L, 1904-1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - M, 1887-1911 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - O-P, 1884-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - R, 1896-1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - S, 1900-1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - W, 1888-1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1917 June (Box 1A, Folder 1)
    - Employees' departure/transfer records (Box 1A)
      - A-D, 1914-1916 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
      - E-L, 1913-1916 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
      - M-O, 1913-1916 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
      - P-Z, 1913-1916 (Box 1A, Folder 5)
    - Admissions book, 1863 January-1915 October; 1 volume (Box Item 2)
    - Connecticut Training School for Feeble Minded admissions book, 1915 October-1917 January; 1 volume (Box Item 3)
    - State patients register
      - 1862 May-1903 November, 1 volume (Box 4)
      - 1903-1913, 1 volume (Box 4)
      - 1906-1913, 1 volume (Box 4)
      - 1912, 1 volume (Box 5)
      - 1912-1913, 1 volume (Box 5)
      - 1913-1915 October, 1 volume (Box 5)
      - Connecticut Training School for Feeble Minded, 1915 October-1917 December; 1 volume (Box Item 6)
    - Connecticut Training School for Feeble Minded daily attendance register, 1914 October-1917 December; 1 volume (Box 7)
    - Weight register, 1911 August-1912 March; 1 volume (Box 7)
    - Financial reports, 1913-1917; 1 volume (Box 7)
  - Connecticut Colony for Epileptics, 1911-1919, 1931
    - Admissions register and daily census, 1914 May-1919 February; 1 volume + loose papers (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Commitment orders
      - A-B, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - C-F, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - G-H, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - L-O, 1913-1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - P-W, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Annual reports, 1911-1914 (Box 1A, Folder 6)
    - Treasurer's annual reports, 1915-1916 (Box 1A, Folder 7)
    - Contracts and bids for construction and equipment, 1910-1913, undated (Box 1A, Folder 8-10)
    - Spur track (Box 1A)
      - Bids and letters, 1911 (Box 1A, Folder 11)
      - Contract, letters and specifications, 1912, 1931 (Box 1A, Folder 12)
    - Notes, 1911 (Box 1A, Folder 13)
    - Employees' time records, 1914 May-1919 February (Box 8)
    - Cash receipts and disbursement ledger, 1914 June-1917 September; 1 volume (Box 8)
- Series 2. Board of Trustees, 1917-1974
  This entire series is RESTRICTED.
  - Legislative act of 1917 establishing Mansfield Training School; Supporting information for Board of Trustees (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (Box 9)
    - 1917 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Includes some correspondence.
    - 1918-1942 (Box 9, Folder 3-9)
    - Trustee's confidential bulletin, 1942 August-November (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 1-11)
    - 1946-1948 June (Box 11, Folder 1-16)
    - 1948 August-1950 May (Box 12, Folder 1-12)
    - 1950 July-1952 January (Box 13, Folder 1-10)
    - 1952 March-1953 November (Box 14, Folder 1-11)
    - 1954 January-1955 September (Box 15, Folder 1-11)
    - 1955 October-1956 December (Box 16, Folder 1-13)
    - 1957 (Box 17, Folder 1-12)
    - 1958 January-1959 February (Box 18, Folder 1-13)
    - 1959 March-1960 May (Box 19, Folder 1-11)
    - 1960 July-1961 September (Box 20, Folder 1-9)
    - 1961 October-1962 October (Box 21, Folder 1-9)
    - 1962 November-1964 February (Box 22, Folder 1-13)
    - 1964 March-1966 March (Box 23, Folder 1-18)
    - 1969-1973 (Box 24, Folder 1-20)
    - 1974 September-December (Box 25, Folder 1-4)
- Series 3. Administration, circa 1891-1987
  Boxes 26-27, and 29 are RESTRICTED.
  Boxes 28, 30-34, 72, and 143-144 are UNRESTRICTED.
  - Joint Committee of Training Schools minutes, 1947-1951, 1968 June 11, 1969 October 21 (Box 26, Folder 1-6)
  - Superintendents' Files, 1919-1971
    - General correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Outgoing correspondence (Box 26)
      - 1959, 1962 December-1963 (Box 26, Folder 8-22)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 27, Folder 1-18)
    - Reference binders 1 and 2, 1920-1941 (Box 27, Folder 19-23)
    - Correspondence regarding literature on courses for mentally retarded children in junior high school, 1941 July-September (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Assistant superintendent position, 1919 February-March (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Sonne (Dr. Hardy), 1942 May-August (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Salvation Army, 1942 March-April (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Stenographer (Grade III), 1942 July (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Sterilization, 1919, 1944 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Strecker, Edward A., 1945 October-November (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Sullivan, Francis T., 1943 October-November (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Opinions of Attorney General binder, circa 1941 (Box 28, Folder 9-17)
    This is from Massachusetts. Coverage dates are 1895-1941.
  - Appointment books (Box 29)
    - 1956, 1 volume (Box 29)
    - 1957, 1 volume (Box 29)
    - 1962, 1 volume (Box 29)
    - 1963, 1 volume (Box 29)
    - 1981 January 1-June 26 (Box 29, Folder 1-3)
  - Christmas cards, 1951 (Box 29, Folder 4-7)
  - Publications (Box 29)
    - A cursory review of issues related to sexuality education / MTS ad hoc Sexuality Information Committee, circa 1970 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Increasing cooperative interaction in the institutionalized retarded / Pritchard, Michael F., 1973 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Family members' handbook, circa 1987 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      A copy is available at
    - Information booklet, circa 1960-1969 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Informational brochure, 1970 November 10 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - A parent's guide to Mansfield Training School, 1977 January (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - The menace of the feeble-minded in Connecticut, circa 1912-1915; photocopy (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Table of organization, Mansfield Training School, 1967 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Telephone directory, 1969 February (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - The Albany Academy bulletin, Annual catalogue of the Albany Academy, Albany, New York, 1931-1932, Vol.II No. 3, 1932 March (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - American Association on Mental Deficiency informational brochure, undated (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - American Association on Mental Deficiency. The Connecticut State Chapter fourth annual conference brochure, undated, 1973 November 17 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Class log / edited and published by graduating class of the Connecticut School for Boys, 1946, 1949-1950, 1952; 4 items (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Congenital syphilis in mental defectives / Benda, Clemens E. and Henry A. Tadgell, 1942 September (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Mental hygiene news / Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene, 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      Additional issues are available at
    - High spots in accomplishments / Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene, circa 1940 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - A directory of private foundations in the state of Connecticut / John Parker Huber, editor, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Hello world! / United States. President's Committee on Mental Retardation, circa 1969-1973 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Memorial sketch of Henry Martin Knight ... late superintendent of the School for Imbeciles at Lakeville, Conn.. / Russel, Gurdon Wadsworth, 1891 (Box 30, Folder 17)
      A copy is available at [CSL call number StLib Conn Doc F33ru]
    - A Communication Guide for the Mansfield Training School, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - A Manual for Foster Parents, 1970 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Connecticut Special Olympics, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970, undated (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Project Challenge - Residential Service Plan, Objective II, Tasks E and F, draft report, 1978 October 1 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Trip - Europe, 1970 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous - publications, circa 1967-1970 (Box 30, Folder 24)
  - Grants -- Application for inservice training, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 25)
  - Grants -- Breaking A Vicious Cycle: Prerequisite for Successful Deinstitutionalization, undated (Box 30, Folder 26)
  - Donations, 1963 January 7-October 30 (Box 31, Folder 1-44)
  - Donations, 1963 November-1964 September 15 (Box 32, Folder 1-52)
  - Donations, 1964 September 21-1965 June 4 (Box 33, Folder 1-59)
  - Donations, 1965 June 7-23 (Box 34, Folder 1-6)
  - Donations -- Christmas 1963, 1963 November 17-1964 January 4 (Box 34, Folder 7-22)
  - Donations -- Christmas 1964 -- Individuals, 1964 November 14-1965 January 8 (Box 34, Folder 23-30)
  - Donations -- Christmas 1964 -- Organizations, 1964 September 23-1965 January 6 (Box 34, Folder 31-37)
  - Chart presentation of administrative and functional relationships of the personnel organization for the Southbury Training School, undated; 1 volume (Box 72)
  - Drug information index cards A-H, undated (Box 143)
  - Drug information index cards I-Z, undated (Box 144)
- Series 4. Mansfield Training School Foundation, 1972-1991
  This series is UNRESTRICTED with the exception of some documents that have been separated and placed in envelope 36.
  - Board of Directors minutes and correspondence, 1972 December 13-1991 April 6 (Box 35, Folder 1-36)
  - Board of Directors correspondence, 1973, 1985, 1987 (Box 35, Folder 37)
  - Agreement and check for van, 1989 February (Box 35, Folder 38)
  - Camp Coventry sidewalk, 1982 July-September (Box 35, Folder 39)
  - Certified public accountants compilation reports, 1987 December 31 (Box 35, Folder 40)
  - Christmas appeal list, 1988 December-1991 January (Box 35, Folder 41)
  - Membership drive list, 1987 December-1988 June (Box 35, Folder 42)
  - Restricted documents (Box Envelope 36)
- Series 5. Civil Defense, 1943-1955
  This entire series is UNRESTRICTED.
  - Civil defense organizational and functional plans, 1953 January (Box 35, Folder 43)
  - Air raid warden forms, 1943 August 12 (Box 35, Folder 44)
    - Barnes-Norling (Box 35, Folder 44)
    - O"Donnell-Wladkowsky (Box 35, Folder 45)
  - State Office of Civil Defense application (blank), circa 1950 (Box 35, Folder 46)